+91 9128946179

vishgaurav786@gmail.com

linkedin - Vishal Gaurav-

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Energy professional with over 3.5 years of experience in the upstream oil and gas sector and an MBA. I have a strong background in production optimization, data analysis, and stakeholder management. I'm eager to apply my technical skills and strategic insights to consulting roles that focus on energy transformation and fostering business growth.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Cairn Oil & Gas, Vedanta Ltd.

April 2023 - Present

Production/Panel Engineer (Upstream)

- Analyzed process data using Historian, Excel, and DOF to enhance operational efficiency and support energy transition goals.
- Operated and optimized DCS, PLC, and SCADA systems for real-time monitoring of 200+ wells and 3 separation facilities.
- Led commissioning of 8 oil wells and 6 injection wells, increasing production by ~1100 BOPD, showcasing strong wells
 management.
- Ensured 100% HSE compliance with zero LTI through JSA, HAZOP, and team safety training for 75+ personnel.
- Drove consulting engagements and client interactions with impactful presentations and a growing focus on renewables.

Production/Panel Engineer (Midstream)

Aug 2021 - April 2023

- Oversaw daily terminal operations including crude oil receipt, storage, and marine dispatch via SPM.
- Ensured safe handling of high-wax crude using 700 km world's largest heated pipeline and insulated storage tanks.
- Proficiency in handling boiler operations, STGs, GEGs, ETP/RO plant, floating roof/fixed roof tanks, tanker loading/unloading activities.
- Orchestrated Single Point Mooring (SPM) loadings for 50+ export tankers, maintaining crude oil movement at 50,000+ BPD
 while adhering to stringent safety and regulatory compliance standards.
- Implemented SCADA-based monitoring for tank levels, flow assurance, and temperature control.
- Supported commissioning of new booster pumps increasing the injection pressure by 50 bar and automation of metering skids (CTMS).
- Enhanced pipeline performance by reviewing PM, pigging plans using **PIDS**, optimizing maintenance schedules, and implementing predictive maintenance strategies using **LDS**.

Indian Oil Corporation Refinery

June 2019 - July 2019

Industrial Trainee

- Assisted in the monitoring and analysis of refinery operations, contributing to the optimization of production processes
- Gained hands-on experience in various departments, including **Maintenance**, **Operations**, **and Quality Control**, improving technical knowledge in industrial processes.

PROJECTS & ACHIEVMENTS

- Certificate of appreciation for commissioning a degassing facility **New low-pressure separator**, **Flare KOD**, **fuel gas scrubber** and **EGF** which led to increasing daily oil production by 200 BBLs.
- Other shutdown/ startup activities include (EGF planned shutdown, water injection network safe shutdown (saving approx. 500 BOPD), startup of whole plant after blackout etc.)
- Received the **Cairn Excellence Award** (TAB) for safely executing the shutdown and startup of the LP separation facility, preventing oil loss, saving **~4500 BOPD**, and ensuring operational continuity with full compliance.
- Polymer processing facility: Led the commissioning of a standalone (1,000 BPD) polymer processing facility, enabling efficient polymer preparation and injection for enhanced oil recovery (EOR).

EDUCATION & CERTIFICATIONS

B.E Chemical + MBA (5yr integrated course), Dr. SSBUICET(Panjab University), 2021

Completed degree with honors with 8.183 CGPA

SSC, Class XII, CBSE School Of Creative Learning, 2015, 81.4%, HSC, Class X, CBSE School Of Creative Learning, 2013, 10 CGPA

SKILLS & ABILITIES

- DCS Operation
- KPI development and analysis
- RCFA and FMEA
- HSE compliance
- Process optimization

Problem solving/ logical thinking Cross function collaboration

Report preparation

Microsoft Excel/Word/Power point

HSE compliance